Ken, you can touch Tsugumi.
研先生…你可以觸碰津輕小姐的
Tsugumi.
津輕小姐…
Tsugumi woke up.
津輕小姐醒了
Tsugumi!
繼實
I will call a doctor.
我去叫醫生來
Okay.
好
AFTER THE PUBLIC BROADCAST OF THE RADIO SHOW WENT OFF THE AIR
（現場廣播風波）
THE MAN APPEARED AGAIN
（引發騷動男子 再次上廣播引起非難）
-Good morning.
-早安
-Boss. -Huh?
-當家 -嗯？
Didn't Ken come home last night?
研昨天沒有回來嗎？
No. He must be with my son.
我兒子也跟他在一起
So, I think he will be okay.
我想應該不需要擔心
Do you think he will come back here?
研先生會回來這裡吧？
I don't know.
這就不知道了
Boss.
社長
It's your cell phone.
手機在響
It's from Seiya.
好像是少爺打來的
Hello?
喂？嗯…
What?
什麼？津輕小姐醒了？
Really?
真的嗎？
Is she all right?
她恢復了嗎？
Ken saved her.
是研先生做的
He awakened Tsugumi's DNA. This may be too difficult for you.
他讓津輕小姐的遺傳因子覺醒了 說了你也不懂吧
Anyway, you are with Ken, right?
總之你跟研先生在一起吧？
Tell him that we are waiting for him to come home.
幫我跟他說我在等他
We are waiting for him.
大家都在等他
Okay.
我知道了
Dad.
老爸
Thank you.
謝謝
INANIWA CORPORATION
（稻庭建築公司）
Stop spacing out.
你在發什麼呆啊？
What happened to Tsugumi?
津輕發生什麼事了？
It's a miracle.
是奇蹟
Miracle?
奇蹟？
My son said thank you.
那傢伙居然跟我道謝…
I didn't ask you that.
根本沒人在問你這個
It's time to work.
好了，快工作吧
I don't know why,
雖然不知道原因
but her brainstem hemorrhage is gone.
但腦幹的出血已經消失了
Did she get well?
所以是治好了嗎？
I can only say that her recovery was a miracle.
現在只能說是奇蹟似地復原了
I haven't seen or heard of any case like this before.
這種例子我從未聽聞
This was because Ken held her hand.
是因為研先生握住了她的手
Huh?
什麼？
Ken cured her and woke her up.
是研先生讓繼實醒來的
I think so too.
我也這麼認為
Haruka.
晴果
You did a good job too.
你也很努力了
Grandma.
外婆
My memories before I became a monster came back.
變成怪物前的記憶回來了
What?
什麼？
I talked all about it on the radio.
我在廣播把這些事情都說出來了
SPECIAL CARE UNIT
（特殊護理病房）
My name is Koroku Yamabe.
我的名字叫做山部呼六
I was an assistant to Dr. Fukashi
我以前在傳染病研究所
at the Infectious Disease Research Institute.
當深志博士的助手
That's when I met Saki and fell in love with her.
我是那時跟早紀小姐相遇，彼此相戀
Dr. Fukashi also fell in love with Saki.
深志博士也愛上了早紀小姐
He raised me from the dead after I died from a contagious disease
博士為了早紀小姐
for the sake of Saki.
讓死於傳染病的我重生了
I…
我…
I was reborn because he fell in love.
是因為博士的愛情而重生的
But after I became a monster,
但是，成為怪物的我
I killed Saki 120 years ago.
在120年前讓早紀小姐死掉了
My sin won't fade away.
這份罪惡不會消失
But you saved Tsugumi.
但是研先生你也救了津輕小姐
You saved her because you carry bacteria.
是研先生的菌救了津輕小姐
Did he save me?
深志先生救了我？
Scientifically, it's not proven yet.
關於這件事，還沒辦法獲得科學證明
Ken.
深志先生
Thank you.
謝謝你
Seiya helped me.
都是託了稻庭前輩的福
I didn't do anything.
我什麼都沒做啊
Seiya.
稻庭前輩
Thank you very much.
謝謝你
Congratulations.
恭喜
What did the listeners say?
聽眾的反應如何？
Most of them didn't really get it.
大部分都是覺得無法理解
He talked about a story from 120 years ago all of a sudden.
突然聽到120年以上的故事 當然不能理解
"Bacteria is disgusting."
有人說：“關於菌類的故事很噁心”
"He killed his girlfriend."
或說：“殺害戀人的危險人物 你們節目還利用他”
Something like that.
大部分都是這樣的意見
There are some people who believe and support Franken too.
當然也有很多人相信怪人 說願意支持他
Amakusa. I told you to deny that he was a monster.
所以天草啊，我不早就叫你否認 他是怪物的事實嗎？
You should have said that we didn't believe him.
要讓聽眾知道我們完全不相信啊
What are you talking about?
你在胡說什麼啊？
Amakusa talked about himself honestly. That's all.
天草只是老實說出自己的想法啊
Huh?
什麼？
It's true that you used Amakusa and Franken.
你們確實是利用了天草跟怪人啊
I don't think you could have finished this topic
想用這個話題
Are you taking his side now?
現在才幫天草說話嗎？
I think Amakusa was brave.
我倒是覺得天草先生的行為很了不起
I was moved.
我很感動
Shut up.
你少說兩句
That guy wouldn't have come to the radio
要是天草先生的話語沒有傳達出去
if he didn't agree with what Amakusa said.
怪人也不會願意上電台吧
Amakusa wanted to be true to him in the end.
天草先生直到最後
Well said.
沒錯
The producer should be responsible for the rest of it.
剩下就是節目的責任了
I am responsible for it too.
我也會負起責任的
Thank you very much.
謝謝您
Tokachi, Ririe.
十勝先生，莉莉惠小姐
It's no doubt that I used the monster in my favor.
我確實是利用了怪物
I asked him to come to the radio.
利用廣播讓這怪物誕生的確實是我
But I liked him in the end.
但是，我到最後 都還是很喜歡這個怪物
And I am relieved that I liked him.
對於自己喜歡這個怪物的事 我鬆了一口氣
I'm sorry.
很抱歉
It's all my fault.
所以全部都是我的責任
It's from Seiya.
是稻庭先生打來的
Hello. This is Amakusa.
你好，我是天草
Hi, Amakusa.
天草先生嗎？
Tsugumi recovered from her illness.
津輕小姐的病復原了
Did Tsugaru recover?
津輕小姐的病好了？
The bacteria he produced might've worked on Tsugaru's DNA.
一定是研先生的菌
Ken can touch Tsugumi now.
研先生現在可以觸碰津輕小姐了
I won't take that kind of interview.
這種採訪請幫我拒絕
It's none of your business, even if I am put in a bad situation.
我的立場什麼的，你們才無法理解呢
Anyway, tell them that I won't see them.
總之都幫我回絕吧
Thanks.
拜託了
Darn it.
煩死了
Shut up.
真夠煩的
How's this?
全都掛斷
Excuse me.
打擾了，教授
Hello.
打擾了
Hey.
哦
Thank you for worrying about me.
教授，讓您擔心了
I won't be surprised at a thing like this.
不，我不會因為這種事 就感到驚訝的
After 120 years,
經過了120年
you finally saved the life of your girlfriend.
你總算拯救了戀人的性命啊
Yes.
是
Well…
不…
I should say that Dr. Fukashi saved you and your girlfriend.
是博士救了你跟你的戀人
That's right.
我也是這麼想的
That's great.
真是太好了
Thank you, Professor Tsurumaru.
這都是託鶴丸教授的福，謝謝您
It's nice to hear that from my senior.
大前輩稱讚我了呢
Do you think Tsugumi's recovery has something to do
教授，津輕小姐會復原
with the story 120 years ago?
跟120年前的事有關嗎？
I don't know if Saki and Tsugumi has any causal relationship.
我不知道早紀小姐 跟津輕小姐有怎樣的因果關係
Maybe after Saki was infected with bacteria,
說不定是因為感染了菌類
it was hidden in her DNA and inherited by Tsugumi.
潛伏在其中的遺傳因子被傳承了下來
In any case, it was DNA that carried it.
無論如何，都是遺傳因子的力量
The DNA of the bacteria that you produced
是你散播的菌類遺傳因子
awakened the DNA of Tsugumi.
讓津輕小姐的遺傳因子覺醒了
Both of you raised a revolution of DNA.
你們兩人可說是掀起了遺傳因子革命
I am worried that we are causing you trouble.
這是否給教授添了麻煩呢？
No worries.
不
I am fine.
我沒什麼大不了的
How are you going to live?
比起這個，你今後打算怎麼過活呢？
That's the problem.
這才比較辛苦吧
I am ready to do anything.
是，我已經做好覺悟了
We will have a party to celebrate her recovery from illness tonight.
教授，今晚我們要慶祝津輕小姐出院
Would you like to join us?
您要不要參加？
No. I am celebrating her recovery by myself.
不，我不會去的
Tsugumi.
津輕小姐
I am fine, no matter what happens in the future.
今後無論多辛苦，我都沒問題的
I decided that I will do what I can do.
我決定要做我能做的事
I appreciate you.
我很感謝你
You are Koroku Yamabe and also Ken Fukashi.
你既是山部呼六先生 也是深志研先生
Yes.
是
I…
我…
I am Tsugumi Tsugaru and also Saki.
是津輕繼實，也是早紀小姐
I love you.
我喜歡你
I have loved you since 120 years ago.
從120年前就喜歡你了
Is that delicious?
好吃嗎？
Yes, I love this.
果然還是很好吃
It's so delicious.
非常好吃
Are you ready?
那要拍囉
Say cheese.
來，笑一個
Here you go.
來
-Thank you.
-謝謝
Congratulations on your recovery, Tsugumi.
那麼，津輕小姐，恭喜你恢復健康
Thank you.
謝謝
-Cheers!
-乾杯！
It's nice to have beer and sing at a restaurant once in a while.
偶爾像這樣在外面喝酒唱歌也不賴啊
You don't have to sing.
唱歌就免了吧，聽社長唱歌
I'm fine.
我沒問題的
If you are fine, why don't you go out, just the two of you?
沒問題的話，你們倆就自己去吧
You are always too extreme.
室園小姐的發言太極端了吧
The boss's singing voice is really bad.
極端的是社長這個音癡吧
You love his voice anyway.
你不就是愛上了那歌聲嗎？
Do you want me to kill you?
小心我殺了你
Murozono.
室園小姐
No.
不能那樣說
It sounds like Ken talks with dignity.
剛才研說的話，分量完全不同呢
It's because he's lived for over 120 years.
這是超過百年以上的份量啊
There is a sake called "One Hundred Years of Solitude".
這麼說來
The boss is such a light-hearted character compared to Ken.
說得一副很有份量的樣子 卻還是輕浮的社長
Fight, it's a song For you who is fighting…
戰鬥，為了戰鬥的你而歌唱
I told you not to sing.
就叫你別唱了
Anyway, it all went well for everyone.
總之，真是可喜可賀
Tsugumi recovered.
津輕小姐出院了，研先生
Now Ken can work with us without worrying about anything.
也能放心在我們這裡工作了
Yes.
是
By the way, can I call you Ken just as before?
話說，我們能照以往一樣 稱呼你研先生嗎？
Why do you ask?
-為什麼這麼問？ -這…
Because you remembered your real name.
因為我們已經知道你的本名了啊
Don't worry about such a thing.
不用執著於這些事吧
Is it okay for you to work with us as a carpenter?
話說回來，你在這裡 繼續當工匠真的好嗎？
You used to be a doctor.
你原本不是醫生嗎？
What are you talking about, Shishikui?
什麼啊，連穴食先生都這麼說
The medical knowledge I learnt is of no use today.
我的醫學知識在現代是沒用武之地的
Do you still want to study medicine?
但你其實是想行醫的吧？
What are you trying to say?
你到底想說什麼啊？
Nothing in particular.
不，我也沒想說什麼
I just want to know what Ken is thinking.
只是在問研先生的想法
I want to work as a carpenter if it's okay for you.
可以的話，我想當個工匠
Good.
這樣啊
Sure, of course.
這不是當然的嗎？
He got used to our job these days.
好不容易才學會這些工作
He should make use of what he's got.
轉換跑道也沒意義吧
But…
但是啊
you may not be able to work with us anymore.
留在我們這裡可能也無法繼續工作
Shishikui! Let's not talk about that.
穴食，這些事就別提了
What do you mean?
怎麼回事？
Our clients started canceling our projects.
工作被取消了
Even the contract where we haven't started the design phase.
連接下來要開始進行 設計階段的工作也是
Why?
為什麼？
I don't know, but they know that Ken lives with us.
我也不知道 但好像是研先生的事曝光了
They are kind of scared.
所以害怕了
Don't worry.
別擔心
That's not what I'm saying.
不會那樣的，我說的不是那樣的事
But, Boss, we should see the reality.
但是當家，這是實際的問題啊
You can leave if you are not happy.
不滿的話可以辭職
Shishikui, Yonago, Iizuka, Mikoto.
穴食、米子、飯塚、美琴
You can work anywhere.
你們到哪裡都能工作的
I will find your new employer.
工作的話，我會負起責任去找來的
I won't go anywhere.
我不會去別的地方的
Me neither.
我也是
But we have no job.
但若是沒有工作…
I have to earn money for my family.
我還要養家餬口啊
I am sorry.
很抱歉
Boss.
社長
I will move out soon.
我會馬上離開的
That's not what I want.
我就說不是這樣了
Listen, Ken.
聽好了，研先生
There is a job that you can say is your lifework.
人們賭上一生的工作不是這樣的
You shouldn't be swayed by those around you.
不是能被世間左右的
If I let you go,
要是我現在放棄了研先生
I may be able to pull my company together again
就算能重新建立公司
but I will lose our relationship.
也無法重新建立我跟研先生的關係
I can't stand it.
我無法忍受這種事，要是這麼做
I will deny my life, my philosophy, my job…
就等於背叛了
and everything.
我的人生、生活方式還有工作
I'm just being selfish. Please forgive me.
這都是出於我的任性，請原諒我吧
Boss.
當家
-I feel the same. -Me too.
-我的心情也是一樣的 -我也是
I love this work as well as Ken no matter what happens.
不管會變怎樣
I can say so because my husband is rich.
當然錢也算是一個誘因
Well, there is always hope in reality.
現實是因為希望而存在
There is always a job in human society.
工作是因為人類而存在
You can't build a house if you can't support a man.
若不能彼此扶持 又怎麼能蓋房子呢？
-Boss!
-說的好，社長 -說的好
He is annoying!
有夠麻煩！
You will be fine.
沒問題的
Just as people in your company have accepted you,
就像建築公司的大家
You will be busy soon.
還會有很多工作進來的
I hope so.
我也希望能這樣
I wish everyone happiness.
大家的幸福是我最大的心願
I wish you happiness too.
津輕小姐也是
I want you to study hard at university.
請在大學好好念書吧
Okay.
是
I want you to be happy.
請你一定要幸福
I am happy.
我很幸福的
INANIWA CORPORATION
（稻庭建築公司）
Boss.
當家
-Are you Mr. Inaniwa? -Yes.
-請問是稻庭先生嗎？ -是
I'm Inaniwa, and I'm the company president.
我就是社長稻庭
We are from the public health center.
我是衛生所的人
The public health center?
衛生所？
What's wrong?
有什麼事嗎？
We came because we had many calls from your neighbors.
有居民抗議，所以我們才來
I'm sure there is a man named Koroku Yamabe.
請問這邊有一位山部呼六先生嗎？
Why are the police here?
這位警察是怎麼回事？
We just want to avoid confusion.
不能造成混亂，請各位協助辦案
We want to hear from him as well.
雖然我是警察，還是要深入了解情況
There is no such man.
這裡沒有叫這名字的男人
Then how about a man called Frankenstein on the radio?
那麼，在廣播被稱為科學怪人的人
I'm sure he lives here.
就在您府上吧？
Then what?
那又怎樣？
We came because we received a request from the neighbors.
既然有居民抱怨 我們也不能不採取行動
He carries bacteria that is not identified.
實體不明的菌類存在於體內的人
We can't just overlook it.
不能放著不管
The neighbors are very scared.
居民們都很害怕啊
What do you want me to do?
那你要我們怎麼做？
We would like to examine him to see if it's true.
我們必須先帶他回去調查是否屬實
Ken won't hurt anyone.
研先生什麼都不會做的
I am responsible for him.
我會負責的
He can come home once he is identified as a human.
只要確認他是完全的人類 馬上會放人的
Boss.
社長
I will go with them.
我願意跟他們走
Ken.
研先生
I knew this would happen once I went on the radio.
既然上了電台，我就做好這個覺悟了
I will accept any punishment.
無論什麼處罰我都願意接受
I don't want to cause trouble to anyone.
我再也不想給任何人添麻煩了
Wait, Ken.
等等，研先生
Seiya.
稻庭前輩，我無論去哪裡
I am not alone.
因為我不是孤獨一人
How about Tsugumi?
津輕小姐又該怎麼辦？
If you go, you won't be able to come back.
若是你去了，可能就無法回來了啊
Wherever I go, I am with Tsugumi.
無論我去到哪裡 心都是跟津輕小姐在一起的
I always wish you happiness.
我永遠會為各位的幸福祈禱
Thank you.
至今
Thank you for everything.
真的很感謝各位
-Ken!
-研 -研先生
Let's go.
麻煩了
Wait, Ken!
等等，研先生
Don't go.
不用去的
You don't have to go.
你沒必要去
You don't have to get pushed around at the whim of humans.
不用再配合人類了
You should live as you like.
研先生你
Who do you think is harmful?
到底誰才是災禍啊？
Run! Go, Ken!
快逃啊，研先生！
Run! Mikoto!
快逃，美琴！
Yes!
好！
Hey!
喂！
-Ken!
-研先生！
-Run. -Go quickly.
-美琴！ -快逃啊
-Go, Ken! -Run!
-快逃啊，研先生！ -快逃！
-Hurry up. -Go Ken.
快逃啊！
Ken! Go!
研先生，快逃啊！
-Go! -Run!
-快！ -快逃啊！
-Run. -Escape.
-快逃啊 -你走吧
-Get out of here. -Run!
-滾開 -快逃！
Murozono.
室園小姐
-Get in the car. -Okay.
-快上車 -是
Hurry up.
快點
INANIWA CORPORATION
（稻庭建築公司）
Are you going without seeing Tsugumi?
不用和津輕見面嗎？
What should I tell her?
我該怎麼跟她說？
Please tell her nothing.
請什麼都別跟她說
Huh?
什麼？
I want Tsugumi to live her own life.
我希望津輕小姐能過自己的人生
But I feel so sorry for Tsugumi.
你這麼說，津輕未免太可憐了
I want to protect her happiness.
我想守護津輕小姐的幸福
I know.
這我懂
But…
但這樣…
But I'll miss you.
這樣未免太寂寞了
Murozono.
室園小姐
Thank you very much.
謝謝你
Call me Mikoto.
叫我美琴啦
I'm sure you are happy that Seiya called you Mikoto.
稻庭前輩願意叫你美琴 真是太好了呢
You don't have to tell me that.
別說這種多餘的話
I…
我也…
I was happy to see you, Mikoto.
很幸運能遇到美琴小姐
You are our friend.
這個…是朋友間的擁抱
Yes.
是
Come back anytime.
隨時歡迎你回來
They will forget about you soon.
毫無關聯的傢伙們馬上就會遺忘的
Come back and see Tsugumi.
也去跟津輕見面吧
Promise me?
一定要喔？
Mikoto.
美琴小姐
Take care of yourself.
請你保重
Take care of yourself too.
保重啊
Goodbye.
再見了
Where is Ken?
研先生呢？
-He went back to the forest. -To the forest?
-回森林去了 -森林？
He told me not to tell Tsugumi.
他要我別跟津輕說
Huh?
什麼？
Ken doesn't want to disturb Tsugumi's life.
研不想打擾津輕的人生
It's cruel to her.
這還真殘酷啊
But…
但是…
That's true love.
那就是愛情吧，真正的愛
Thank you…
謝謝
Mikoto.
美琴
Let's go home.
回去吧
Yeah.
好
How should I call you?
我該怎麼叫你呢？
Young master?
叫你少爺嗎？
Do you want me to kill you?
我殺你喔
Not like that, like this?
不是“我殺你喔” 是“小心我殺你”
Isn't that the same?
不是一樣嗎？
Tsugumi.
津輕小姐
Where is Ken?
深志先生呢？
Ken…
研先生他…
We tried.
是我們擅自…
He went back to the forest, didn't he?
他回森林了吧？
Yes.
對
He said he wanted to protect your happiness.
他說想守護你的幸福
Tsugumi.
津輕小姐
Hello.
辛苦了
The police and the media are trying to find Franken.
媒體跟警方好像一直在追查怪人
He hasn't been found yet.
但似乎還是下落不明
You don't have to call him Franken anymore.
已經沒必要叫他怪人了吧
Everyone knows the facts.
既然都變成事實了
Our radio show is going to be cut by the end of this month.
我們節目只能做到這個月了
We made a bet and it's out of control.
造成世間這麼大的騷動
We had no choice.
廣播局也不能不收拾殘局
I am very sorry.
很抱歉
I told you that it wasn't your fault.
又不是你的錯
We will keep the show until the next program is ready.
在準備新節目期間，還是會持續播放
But Amakusa's Corner is already canceled.
但天草的單元已經決定取消了
-Sorry. -No.
-很抱歉 -不
I understand.
我明白了
Thank you very much for everything.
長久以來，真的很感謝各位的照顧
TOKYO MUSASHI RADIO STATION
（東京武藏廣播局）
Amakusa!
天草先生
You won't be called for any program for a while.
我想…我會暫時被從節目放逐
But I won't give up.
但我不會放棄的
I will launch something interesting soon.
我會再想出更有趣的企畫的
I…
我…
I didn't want a monster to come to our show.
不是想讓怪物上節目
I just wanted to make a show like a monster.
而是想做出像怪物一樣的節目
I won't give up my dream.
今後我也不會放棄這夢想的
So…
所以
please be prepared, Amakusa.
天草先生，也請你隨時做好準備吧
Okay.
我明白了
Thank you.
謝謝
It was a mystery.
但是，真的很不可思議呢
He was a monster.
同樣是怪物
But he was like poison to someone and medicine to the other.
遇上不同人 會變成毒藥，也會變成解藥
Well,
這…畢竟這都是我們的心 製造出來的啊
to create a monster and a radio show.
無論是怪物還是廣播
You are scary…
雖然有點可怕
but funny.
但果然還是很有趣呢
See you. Take care.
那麼，請你保重
You too, Ushi-chan.
阿牛你也保重
TOKYO MUSASHI BROADCASTING
（東京武藏廣播局）
ASK AMAKUSA!
（問問天草吧）
I hope that Ken is having fun now.
研先生現在 如果也覺得很有趣就好了
I'm sure you remember Franken.
關於那位科學怪人
He is still missing.
-還是下落不明 -嗯
I hope that no one will find him.
但如果可以的話
Our show found him.
這…說來說去 要是找到了，我們節目要負責的
So, I want to hide him. I will be responsible.
所以我想負起責任 把他藏起來，我想包庇他
You will be fired.
說這種話，會被開除的
I don't care.
才不會呢
Don't worry about me.
我的身體已經沒事了
I am perfectly fine.
就像這樣，活蹦亂跳的
I am even better than before.
或許比你還健康呢
I think I will not die.
說不定我變成不死之身了
Don't make me scared.
別說這麼可怕的事
No, Tokachi.
十勝先生你是不行的
What do you mean, "no"?
什麼叫我不行啊？
Amakusa is doing fine.
天草也很有精神的
He will come back to the radio someday.
總有一天他會回廣播的
Listen to his program when he's back, Franken.
到時再讓我們 聽聽你的聲音吧，怪人
Here is a song for Amakusa, who was fired from the radio station.
那麼送上一曲
Amakusa song.
請聽這首《天草之歌》
Here it goes. Amakusa song.
那麼，就來聽聽天草之歌吧
Here it goes.
請
Hurry up!
還不快放！
Here it goes!
請！
MIEJI DORI BLOCK 1 SHIBUYA, SHIBUYA WARD
（明治街 澀谷區澀谷一區）
It's time for you and I
你和我的時間
Evolutionary theory for you and I
我和你的進化論
If you are worrying about something…
有煩惱就問天草
Ask Amakusa
去問問天草吧
Ken.
深志先生
Ken?
深志先生？
Ken!
深志先生！
Check the website
長野信濃大學農學部
They announced that they found Akanarikamitake mushrooms.
在官網上說發現了赤成神菇
It's only supposed to grow in a primeval coniferous forest,
上面寫著 “找到了只會在針葉樹原生林”
but they said they found it.
才會找到的赤成神菇
This must be Akanarikamitake-modoki.
這一定是剛摘下來的赤成神菇
It must be Ken.
是研先生啊
Ken.
深志先生
I…
我是…
I came to find this.
來找這個的
I have…
一直…
I've always been loving you.
喜歡著你
I missed you.
我一直好想見你
Tsugumi.
津輕小姐
Ken.
研先生
Ken!
研先生！
I wanted to see you.
研先生，我好想見你
Seiya!
稻庭前輩
Professor Tsurumaru.
鶴丸教授
I'm glad that you are fine.
看到你沒事就好了
-Please take a look at this. -Huh?
教授，請看這個
Ken.
研先生
I want to show you something.
我們有東西想給你看
Let's go together.
一起去吧
Okay.
是
Look.
這是為了
We bought this for fieldwork.
實地調查而購入的
Fieldwork?
實地調查？
We can culture bacteria here.
有了這個就能培養菌類
Let's get in.
進去吧
We cultured bacteria here
我們會在這裡培養菌類
and brought it to the university to examine.
拿去大學進行研究
I can go to any forest in Japan by driving this car.
若是在國內的森林 有這台車，哪裡都能去
I will take turns with Tsugumi to be with you
津輕小姐跟我會輪流 陪在研先生你身邊
and culture bacteria.
培養重要的菌類
I'm sure we can put your bacteria to use.
一定會派上用場的
This is not for you, it's all for us.
這不是為了你，而是為了我們
It's the ego of a scientist.
這是科學者的自私
I would like you to study with us.
能請你跟我們一起學習嗎？
Study?
-學習？ -學習你自己
A doctor of myself?
我…要成為我自己的博士？
You never know what kind of bacteria you will discharge.
今後無論你釋放出什麼菌類都行
I want you to create many bacteria that are nice to humans if possible.
可以的話
And you will study about the bacteria that you create
而這些菌類就由你自己來研究
as a member of our team, of course.
當然是以我們這研究小組的成員身分
We want to cure incurable diseases.
這是為了盡可能減少難治疾病
This is to pass the baton of life from you.
這會讓你將生命延續下去
It's my dream.
這也是我的夢想
Let's make a revolution together.
一起掀起革命吧
I…
我…
Can I help humans?
能幫上人類嗎？
We will prove it with you from now on.
這件事接下來才要慢慢證明呢
I promise you that we will prove it.
一定能證明的
Ken.
研先生
Yes.
是
I understand.
我知道了
Love poison of devils and angels
惡魔跟天使的春藥
The future is always a story of idealism
未來總是理想論
If you are worried about something…
有煩惱就問天草
Ask Amakusa
去問問天草吧
Hi. This is Junpei Amakusa.
好的，我是天草純平
I will answer the phone to solve the problem
今天也會直接接起電話
that you are worrying about.
傾聽您的煩惱
-Hello.
-你好
Hi. This is Junpei Amakusa.
我是天草純平
Please tell me what you are worried about.
請讓我聽聽您的煩惱
Yes.
是，我最近
I can't go out because I'm scared of people.
我變得好害怕人類，都沒辦法出門
-I see. -This is incredible.
-原來如此啊 -太棒了
Let's do this.
總之
Don't think that there is a town outside.
既然如此，就別把外面當成街道
Just think that it's a forest when you go out.
而是想成森林，出門看看吧
A forest?
森林嗎？
You don't have to interact with others.
就算不跟人接觸也行
When you see someone,
如果遇上了什麼人
don't worry about what others think of you.
不用想對方怎麼看待自己
Imagine that others may think the same way as you think.
而是試著想想對方或許也跟自己一樣
Maybe they are scared of people as well.
或許也很害怕人類
Then imagine what you would say to them.
如果能這麼想
I passed the exam.
我考試通過了
You are scared of people because you can imagine what others think.
害怕人類的這種想像力也是有功用的
When you want to tell people that they don't have to be scared,
如果想跟對方說一句“不用害怕”
then you will be able to love someone naturally.
總有一天
Tsugumi.
津輕小姐
This is a very nice tree.
這是很棒的樹木
It's full of vital energy.
充滿了生命力
I'm sure I can produce good bacteria from it.
一定會產出很棒的菌的
-Will you try? -Sure.
-拜託了 -是
Let's go.
那…我們走吧
Okay.
是
A FEW DECADES LATER
（數十年後）
-Hi. -Hello.
-午安 -歡迎
Here is a new bacteria and its record.
這是新的菌種跟研究紀錄
Thank you.
謝謝
How are Seiya and Mikoto doing?
稻庭前輩
Grandpa and Grandma always want to see you, Ken.
爺爺奶奶也總是說很想見研先生呢
I will come visit them soon.
我會再去玩的
Ken.
研先生
It's been a year since Tsugumi passed away.
在津輕女士過世後 差不多也要過一年了
Are you going to stay here?
您打算一直待在這裡嗎？
People in the world are grateful for you.
全世界的人都很感謝研先生您呢
This is where I feel at home the most.
我待在這裡最安心
I will stay here, with Tsugumi.
我會在這裡陪著津輕小姐
Tsugumi must be happy.
津輕女士還真幸福呢
Let me bring them back.
那我就先收下了
I promise you that we will develop a great medicine again.
一定會再開發出良藥的
I bet so.
拜託了
THIS DRAMA IS A WORK OF FICTION
（本劇純屬虛構）